Guide to the Henry Thomas James Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Henry Thomas James papers
1958-1993
SC0089
James, Henry Thomas, 1915-
20 Linear feet
Professional correspondence, administrative records, materials relating to educational conferences held at Stanford, and some research materials for James' comparative study of educational systems in various states.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of H. Thomas James, 1970, 1997.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of education at Stanford (1958-1970) and dean of School of Education from June 1966 to August 1970 when he resigned to become president of the Spencer Foundation in Chicago.
Description of the Collection
Professional correspondence, administrative records, materials relating to educational conferences held at Stanford, and some research materials for James' comparative study of educational systems in various states.
Access Terms
James, Henry Thomas, 1915-; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education. Faculty.; Education--Study and teaching
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-1997-027
  - Publications by H. Thomas James:
    - The New Cult of Efficiency and Education. University of Pittsburgh Press, 1968 (Horace Mann Lecture) (Box 1)
    - The Nation's Report Card; Improving the Assessment of Student Achievement. National Academy of Education, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Excellence in Administration: the Dynamics of Leadership. School of Education, Stanford University [1962] (Box 1)
  - Other publications:
    - W. C. McKern, The Clam River Focus. Milwaukee Public Museum Publications in Anthropology, 1963 (Inscribed to James by author) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1965, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Draft (found in The Nation's Report Card) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Papers
  - Alkin, M. (Box 1)
  - Allen, J. (Box 1)
  - Bane, J. (Box 1)
  - Bendiner, R. (Box 1)
  - Benson, C. (Box 1)
  - Beneviste, G. (Box 1)
  - Bertolaet, F. (Box 1)
  - Binford, R. (Box 1)
  - Bolton, D. (Box 1)
  - Bowman, T. (Box 1)
  - Boyan, N. (Box 1)
  - Briner, C. (Box 1)
  - Burke, A. (Box 1)
  - Burkhead, J. (Box 1)
  - Butler, C. (Box 1)
  - Carson, W. (Box 1)
  - Chamberlain, G. (Box 1)
  - Chase (Box 1)
  - Cognetta, R. (Box 1)
  - Cohen, D. (Box 1)
  - Cremin, L. (Box 1)
  - Crockenberg, V. (Box 1)
  - Cronin, J. (Box 1)
  - Cronin, T. (Box 1)
  - Duffy, P. (Box 1)
  - Dyck, H. (Box 1)
  - Evans, D. (Box 1)
  - Fairley, R. (Box 1)
  - Falk, D. (Box 1)
  - Feiock, V. (Box 1)
  - Figgins, G. (Box 1)
  - Fine, A. (Box 1)
  - Funk, R. (Box 1)
  - Gardner, J. (Box 1)
  - Garms, W. (Box 1)
  - Gonzales, S. (Box 1)
  - Gutherie, J. (Box 1)
  - Haley, F. (Box 1)
  - Hannon, J. (Box 1)
  - Hanson, N. (Box 1)
  - Harlow, J. (Box 1)
  - Harvey, L. (Box 1)
  - Hirsch, W. (Box 1)
  - Howe, H. (Box 1)
  - Jacobs, W. (Box 1)
  - Johns, R. (Box 1)
  - Johnson, L. (Box 1)
  - Keepes, B. (Box 1)
  - Keppel, F. (Box 1)
  - Konrad, A. (Box 2)
  - Lamp, R. (Box 2)
  - Loveless, E. (Box 2)
  - Lyon, H. (Box 2)
  - Lytle, J. (Box 2)
  - Morisett, L. (Box 2)
  - Morss, H. (Box 2)
  - Morphet, E. (Box 2)
  - Minar, D. (Box 2)
  - Miller, M. (Box 2)
  - Marden, R. (Box 2)
  - Manning, W. (Box 2)
  - Magid, F. (Box 2)
  - McVey, R. (Box 2)
  - McCarthy, D. (Box 2)
  - Nelson, F. (Box 2)
  - Paez, J. (Box 2)
  - Penny, W. (Box 2)
  - Perlberg, Arye (Box 2)
  - Polley, T. (Box 2)
  - Potter, C. (Box 2)
  - Pucinski, R. (Box 2)
  - Ross, P. (Box 2)
  - Rowe, H. (Box 2)
  - Sanford, T. (Box 2)
  - Sarpa & Moore (Box 2)
  - Scribner, J. (Box 2)
  - Shapiro, D. (Box 2)
  - Sizer, T. (Box 2)
  - Stover, C. (Box 2)
  - Thomas, J. (Box 2)
  - Van Gorder, E. (Box 2)
  - Von Stoephasius, R. (Box 2)
  - Willis, B. (Box 2)
  - Wilsey, C. (Box 2)
  - Associations - miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Committees on studies (AACTE) (Box 2)
  - AACTE American Assn. of Colleges for Teacher Education (Box 2)
  - AERJ American Educational Research Journal (Box 2)
  - Editorial board (AERJ) (Box 2)
  - ASBO Assn of School Business Officials (Box 2)
  - CASBO California Assn of Public School Business Officials (Box 2)
  - CASA California Assn. of School Administrators (Box 2)
  - Administrative policies committee (CASA) (Box 3)
  - CASA (Section VII) (Box 3)
  - CERA California Education Research Assn. (Box 3)
  - CESAA California Elementary School Admin. Assn. (Box 3)
  - CESC California Education Study Council (Box 3)
  - CSBA California School Boards Association (Box 3)
  - CTA California Teachers Association (Box 3)
  - NASBE National Conference of Professors of Educational Administration (Box 3)
  - NCSPS National Committee for Support of Public Schools (Box 3)
  - NEA National Educational Association (Box 3)
  - Finance Conference (NEA) (Box 3)
  - NSBA National School Boards Association (Box 3)
  - PDK Phi Delta Kappa (Box 3)
  - UCEA University Council for Educational Administration (Box 3)
  - UCEA "Business-Education Interface" (Box 3)
  - UCEA career development seminars (Box 3)
  - Chief state school officers (Box 3)
  - Christian Science Monitor (Box 3)
  - Commission on education (Box 3)
  - Commission for economic development (Box 3)
  - Commission on instructional technology (Box 3)
  - Commission of international exchange of students (Elizabeth Lam-Fulbright) (Box 3)
  - Contract (H.E.W. Field reader contract) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Alaska (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Big Cities (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Carnegie (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - General Correspondence, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Great Cities Research Council (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - School Boards (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - School Planning Lab. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - University of Chicago (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - University of Wisconsin (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - U. S. Office of Education (Box 3)
  - Council for Basic Education (Box 3)
  - Danforth foundation (Box 3)
  - Delaware: State Department of Education (Box 3)
  - Denver (Box 3)
  - Education USA (Box 3)
  - Education Commission of the US (Box 3)
  - Education industry (Ivy Lee) (Box 3)
  - Educational leadership (Box 3)
  - ERIC (Box 3)
  - Federal employment applications (Box 3)
  - Federal folder (Box 3)
  - Fellowships (Box 3)
  - OE Fellowships (Box 3)
  - Fellowship applications (Box 3)
  - Finance papers (Box 3)
  - Florida (Box 3)
  - Foundations (Box 3)
  - General learning corporation (Box 4)
  - Governor's Commission on Educational Reform June 24 (Box 4)
  - Guggenheim grant (Box 4)
  - Houghton Mifflin company (Box 4)
  - Harvard University (Box 4)
  - Institute for Educational Development (Marland) (Box 4)
  - Jan 30-31 Atlanta? OE Consultants (Marland) (Box 4)
  - Institute for Educational Development (Marland) (Box 4)
  - May 7-9 OE Consultants (Box 4)
  - Internships (Box 4)
  - November 4 Rand Corporation speech (Box 4)
  - Invitations declined (Box 4)
  - Educational heads of private institutions, 1969 February (Box 4)
  - Kellog Foundation (Box 4)
  - Los Angeles (Box 4)
  - McGraw Hill (critical review) (Box 4)
  - Macmillan Company (Box 4)
  - February 19 Washington DC Marjorie Webster Jr. College (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous conferences (Box 4)
  - 8 state project (Montana) (Box 4)
  - New Mexico (Box 4)
  - August 15 Albany 1967, 1967 August 15 (Box 4)
  - New York (Box 4)
  - Oct. 24-25 Gainsville National Educational ? Project (Box 4)
  - Oakland screen (Box 4)
  - NY State Commission of Education Screen (Box 4)
  - Clippings - James (Box 4)
  - Lower Merion screening (Box 4)
  - Bonita screening commission (Box 4)
  - Screening SF schools (Box 4)
  - July 13 - Washington Ed. Professions Development Act. (Box 4)
  - Year round school (Box 4)
  - U. S. Office of Education (Box 4)
  - USOE - SF (Box 4)
  - USOE Board of Research (Box 4)
  - Vermont (Box 4)
  - West Virginia (Box 4)
  - Summer '68 Wilton Park, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Wisconsin (Box 4)
  - Wyoming, Casper (Box 4)
  - U. S. General Accounting Office of Admin. Services (Box 5)
  - USOE - EPDA consultants (Box 5)
  - USOE - Board of research field readers contracts (Box 5)
  - USOE - Board of higher education (Box 5)
  - Urban coalition (mid-peninsula) (Box 5)
  - University of California Irvine (Box 5)
  - UCLA Center for study of education (Box 5)
  - UNESCO (Box 5)
  - Nov. 23-24 UNESCO Conference (Sunset Magazine - Middlefield and Willow) (Box 5)
  - Systems analysis (Box 5)
  - Syracuse University research corporation (Box 5)
  - Aug. David Porter Syracuse (Box 5)
  - Studies - other (Box 5)
  - SAIPAN Aug. 19-24 (James) (Box 5)
  - Theory into practice (Box 5)
  - Teachers College, Columbia University (Box 5)
  - Carnegie - task force on education (Box 5)
  - Task force on urban education (Box 5)
  - Jan. 7 - Nixon task force (Box 5)
  - Hawaii (Box 6)
  - Ford (Com. on Fellowships, Internships and Research awards vis-a-vis Latin America) (Box 6)
  - Ford - Brown (Box 6)
  - Ford - (finance project nomination) (Box 6)
  - Ford - (finance project - no nominations) (Box 6)
  - Ford grant (#68-24) Finance project, 1967 November (Box 6)
  - The Cleveland conference (Box 6)
  - Jamaica, 1968 June 16-19 (Box 6)
  - Carnegie proposal - extended study (Box 6)
  - Carnegie proposal - first year, 1963 December 1 - 1964 November 30 (Box 6)
  - Chile, 1966 June 11-19 (Box 6)
  - Columbia, 1967 March 18-31 (Box 6)
  - Brazil (Box 6)
  - Alaska State Department of Education (Box 6)
  - Dean/BIA (Box 6)
  - Oct. 19-24 Alaska (Cordova) (Box 6)
  - Alaska (Box 6)
  - Alaska (Box 6)
  - Alaska Study Sept. 15-16 (Box 6)
  - April 22 Oregon (Box 6)
  - University of Oregon NCATE, 1969 January 20-22 (Box 6)
  - Center for Advanced Study of Education Admin. National Advisory Comm., 1967-1970 (Box 6)
  - PACE San Mateo County (Box 6)
  - PA Citizens Advisory Committee (Box 6)
  - PEDR (Box 6)
  - Penisula school (Box 6)
  - Pennsylvania (Box 6)
  - Harrisburg (Box 6)
  - Pittsburg (Box 6)
  - Coordinating council of higher education (Box 7)
  - CEMREL (St. Louis) (Box 7)
  - Carnegie corporation (Box 7)
  - Campbell unified school district (Box 7)
  - American school board journal (Box 7)
  - Allyn & Bacon Inc. (Box 7)
  - Administrator's notebook (Box 7)
  - Committee on nominations (AERA) (Box 7)
  - AERA American Education Research Association (Box 7)
  - March 25 AERA Minneapolis (Box 7)
  - AERA readings (Box 7)
  - AASA American Association of School Administrators (Box 7)
  - AASA National Assessment of Education Progress (Box 7)
  - Committee on administrator education (Box 7)
  - Dec. 3 Committee on administrative studies (Box 7)
  - Committee on advanced graduate degrees (Box 7)
  - CAGD subcommittee on admissions (Box 7)
  - Committee on faculty research & publication (Box 7)
  - Committee on international studies (Box 7)
  - Committee on metropolitan studies (Box 7)
  - Committee on teacher education (Box 7)
  - Committee on university policy (Box 7)
  - Committee on urban and regional studies (Box 7)
  - Dean's meetings (Box 7)
  - Fund raising objectives, opportunities... (Box 7)
  - Governmental policies toward higher education (Box 7)
  - Institute of public policy analysis (Box 7)
  - Postdoctoral program (Box 7)
  - Principles' advisory committee (Box 7)
  - Registrar's advisory committee (Box 7)
  - Research and development center (Box 7)
  - Research traineeship program (Box 7)
  - Search committee (Dean, School of Education), 1966 (Box 7)
  - Special subcommittee on education (Box 8)
  - School board bibliography (annotated) (Box 8)
  - SF school (Box 8)
  - San Diego county schools (Box 8)
  - Program accounting (Hutchin's correspondence) (Box 8)
  - Program budgeting (Box 8)
  - Responsive environments (Box 8)
  - Public affairs fellowship program (Box 8)
  - Placement - appointments (Box 8)
  - University of Toronto MA(T) PROG (Box 8)
  - Philadelphia - James (Box 8)
  - Iolani school - visit, 1969 November (Box 8)
  - Hawaii (new) March 30-April 4 (Box 8)
  - Dean James research files for his study on educational systems in the various states (Box 9-10)
    - Background: for great cities school systems (Box 9)
    - Collected information (Box 9)
    - Rough drafts (Box 9)
    - Printed reports profect I.I.D.- staff (Box 9)
    - Guthrie project (Box 9)
    - Kelly project (Box 9)
    - Chicago (Box 9)
    - District of Columbia (Box 9)
    - L.A. rough work (Box 9)
    - L.A. first draft (Box 9)
    - Pittsburg (Box 9)
    - St. Louis (Box 9)
    - San Francisco (Box 9)
    - Alabama (Box 10)
    - Alaska (Box 10)
    - Arizona (Box 10)
    - Arkansas (Box 10)
    - Colorado (Box 10)
    - Connecticut (Box 10)
    - District of Columbia (Box 10)
    - Florida (Box 10)
    - Georgia (Box 10)
    - Hawaii (Box 10)
    - Idaho (Box 10)
    - Illinois (Box 10)
    - Indiana (Box 10)
    - Iowa (Box 10)
    - Kansas (Box 10)
    - Kentucky (Box 10)
    - Maine (Box 10)
    - Maryland (Box 10)
    - Massachusetts (Box 10)
    - Minnesota (Box 10)
    - Mississippi (Box 10)
    - Missouri (Box 10)
    - Montana (Box 10)
    - New Hampshire (Box 10)
    - New Jersey (Box 10)
    - Nevada (Box 10)
    - North Carolina (Box 10)
    - North Dakota (Box 10)
    - Ohio (Box 10)
    - Oklahoma (Box 10)
    - Oregon (Box 10)
    - Pennsylvania (Box 10)
    - Rhode Island (Box 10)
    - South Carolina (Box 10)
    - Tennesee (Box 10)
    - Texas (Box 10)
    - Utah (Box 10)
    - Vermont (Box 10)
    - Virginia (Box 10)
    - Washington (Box 10)
    - West Virginia (Box 10)
    - Wisconsin (Box 10)
    - Wyoming (Box 10)
    - Canal Zone (Box 10)
    - Guam (Box 10)
    - Puerto Rico (Box 10)
    - Virgin Islands (Box 10)
  - Advisory committee on public school finance (Box 11)
  - Booz, Allen and Hamilton (Chicago) (Box 11)
  - California constitutional revision commission (Box 11)
  - California Journal of Secondary Education (Box 11)
  - Chicago citizens school committee (Box 11)
  - Chico State College, 1967 May 19-20 (Box 11)
  - Civil rights commission (Box 11)
  - Commitee for economic development (Box 11)
  - Committee on systems analysis (Box 11)
  - Conference on school administrators on teachers negotiations, Stanford, 1967 July (Box 11)
  - Cornell School Board Studies (COEL) (Box 11)
  - Credential committee (criteria for standard admin. cred.) Schrupp (Box 11)
  - House Special Subcommittee on Education. Room 19415, Fed. Office Bldg., SF, 9:45-11:00 am, 1966 December 12 (Box 11)
  - IBM data processing and public school finance (potential project) (Box 11)
  - King County study (Washington) (Box 11)
  - Michigan finance study (National Advisory Committee) (Box 11)
  - Project public information conference, 1967 November 30 - December 1 (Box 11)
  - Project public information conference, 1967 November 30 - December 1 (Box 11)
  - Proposal - Fremont Unified School District (Box 11)
  - Proposal - Nebraska (Box 11)
  - Proposals - Network (Ford) (Box 11)
  - Redwood Shores study (Box 11)
  - Research Council (Great Cities) 1:30 pm Milwaukie, Hotel Pfiester, 1966 November 19 (Box 11)
  - Research digest (Box 11)
  - School Board workship - Chicago (Box 11)
  - Study - University of Oregon (Box 11)
  - Syracuse studies (Box 11)
  - Title III - Elementary and Secondary Education Act, 1965 (Box 11)
  - USOE - Bureau of Research (Box 11)
  - USOE - Regional Meeting, Colorado Springs, Colorado, 1966 October 16-18 (Box 11)
  - UCLA study (Box 11)
  - University of Florida study (Box 11)
  - University of Illinois study (Box 11)
  - University of Oklahoma (Norman), Mid-American Center for Urban Education Advisory Council (Box 12)
  - University of Pennsylvania study (Box 12)
  - Vocational education - Bushnell (Box 12)
  - Wisconsin School Board study (Box 12)
  - Working papers - master file (do not remove contents) (Box 12)
  - Yardstick project (Pinkham) (Box 12)
  - Alaska - Material on (Box 12)
  - American scholars - Fulbright conference (Box 12)
  - CACER - California Advisory Council on Education Research (Box 12)
  - CAPEE - California Association of Professors in Elementary Education (Box 12)
  - CASSA - California Association of Secondary School Administrators (Box 12)
  - CASSA-CASA - Spring conference; Harvey's Resort Hotel, Stateline, 1965 May 6-8 (Box 12)
  - CCPSA - California Commission of Public School Administration (Box 12)
  - CCUFA - California College and University Faculty Association (Box 12)
  - California State Poly Education Center; San Dimas, 1965 October 6-7 (Box 12)
  - The Cleveland conference; Chicago, 1965 December 3-4 (Box 12)
  - Commendations - Cubberley conference (Box 12)
  - Committee of seven - Title V (Box 12)
  - Conference on administation of educational research; Chicago, 1965 February 9 (Box 12)
  - 92nd convocation, University of State of NY; Albany, NY, 1966 September 21 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, to and from Elizabeth Lam, Fulbright Conf. (Box 12)
  - Correspondence - Research Council (Box 12)
  - Final report - school board (Box 12)
  - Final report - school finance studies (Box 12)
  - Great cities research council (Box 12)
  - IIEP seminar; Paris, 1966 June 27 - July 8 (Box 12)
  - ITM project, instructional technology and media project (Box 12)
  - Logs - both projects (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous - Fulbright conference (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 12)
  - NEA committee on educational finance, Chicago, Illinois, Sherman House, 1965 April 4-7 (Box 12)
  - NSSE yearbook (Box 12)
  - New Haven Unified School District (Union City) (Box 12)
  - Planning committee Fulbright conference (Box 12)
  - Progress report - SAE 2389 (Box 12)
  - Publication of Cubberley conference papers (correspondence regarding) (Box 12)
  - San Francisco - correspondence (Box 13)
  - Staff seminars (Box 13)
  - Cubberley conference, H, Thomas James Director (summary papers), 1962 (Box 13)
  - Cubberley conference, publication notices of Excellence in Administration: The Dynamics of Leadership, 1962 (Box 13)
  - Montana (Box 13)
  - Nevada, Las Vegas (Box 13)
  - New Mexico, Albequerque (Box 13)
  - New York, State Dept. of Education (Box 13)
  - Oregon, State Dept. of Education (Box 13)
  - Papers - Cubberley conference (Box 13)
  - San Diego, statewide review committeefor the project to revise Division 7 of the California Education Code (Box 13)
  - A.E.R.H. (Box 13)
  - Bookings - review of Tyler's paper for "Agenda for a Nation" (Box 13)
  - Careers in education conference; 9;00 am; Dinkelspiel auditorium, 1966 December 3 (Box 13)
  - Cleveland conference, Hilton Hotel, Chicago, 1966 December 2-3 (Box 13)
  - Jm. Cronin - memos and papers (Box 13)
  - Dr. James (Box 13)
  - School board (Box 13)
  - Travel (Box 13)